The second type of error is often the toughest
to discover, a logic error.
With a logic error, there is no syntax problem
with the code, and the code does not cause
a crash, but the code does not perform the
way one expects it to when the code is run.
We saw, in an earlier domain, how the order
of the code determines the logic in how code
flows, and sometimes, we need to rearrange
code to get it to flow in the correct order
logically.
However, many logic errors stem from either
flawed formulas or the wrong information being
given to someone to use in a formula.
Take, for example, this 512-logic file.
I’m only focusing on one piece of logic
in this code so we can better identify logic
errors.
We have three variables on lines 1 through
3, the second variable being a calculation.
Then, on line 5, we have a print statement
that calculates the score plus the bonus and
then applies the multiplier, or so we think.
I have comments in the code on line 2 to calculate
the bonus and then the expected result on
line 5.
Let’s run this code.
The result is 3600, not 6600.
Logically, one could argue that 3000 plus
300 is 3300, and multiplied by two is 6600.
But do you spot the logic problem in the code?
It’s not that the variable on line 2 is
derived from line 1’s value.
That happens quite a bit in programming.
We need to know and apply the order of operations
to identify the logic error, a concept we
covered in detail earlier in the course.
What’s happening with the code is that the
bonus and multiplier calculation is happening
first because multiplication happens before
addition in order of operations.
Thus, the logic fix is to add parentheses
around the score plus the bonus to make that
calculation happen first.
I will make the change, rerun the code, and
get the anticipated result of 6600.
Identifying logic errors is crucial to working
well with any programming language, as logic
errors do not return any error message and
thus can be very tough and time-consuming
to identify.
The more we know what types of logic errors
to expect, the easier they are to identify.